<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<element name="Aasimar" type="Race" source="Player's Handbook (2024)" id="ID_SPECIES_AASIMAR">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">Aasimar bear within their souls the light of the heavens. They are descended from humans with a touch of the power of Mount Celestia, the divine realm of many lawful good deities. Aasimar are born to serve as champions of the gods, their births hailed as blessed events. They are a people of otherworldly visages, with luminous features that reveal their celestial heritage.</p>
			<h4>CELESTIAL CHAMPIONS</h4>
			<p>Aasimar are placed in the world to serve as guardians of law and good. Their patrons expect them to strike at evil, lead by example, and further the cause of justice.</p>
			<p class="indent">From an early age, an aasimar receives visions and guidance from celestial entities via dreams. These dreams help shape an aasimar, granting a sense of destiny and a desire for righteousness.</p>
			<p class="indent">Each aasimar can count a specific celestial agent of the gods as a guide. This entity is typically a deva, an angel who acts as a messenger to the mortal world.</p>
			<h4>HIDDEN WANDERERS</h4>
			<p>While aasimar are strident foes of evil, they typically prefer to keep a low profile. An aasimar inevitably draws the attention of evil cultists, fiends, and other enemies of good, all of whom would be eager to strike down a celestial champion if they had the chance.</p>
			<p class="indent">When traveling, aasimar prefer hoods, closed helms, and other gear that allows them to conceal their identities. They nevertheless have no compunction about striking openly at evil. The secrecy they desire is never worth endangering the innocent.</p>
			<h4>AASIMAR GUIDES</h4>
			<p>An aasimar, except for one who has turned to evil, has a link to an angelic being. That being - usually a deva - provides guidance to the aasimar, though this connection functions only in dreams. As such, the guidance is not a direct command or a simple spoken word. Instead, the aasimar receives visions, prophecies, and feelings.</p>
			<p class="indent">The angelic being is far from omniscient. Its guidance is based on its understanding of the tenets of law and good, and it might have insight into combating especially powerful evils that it knows about.</p>
			<p class="indent">As part of fleshing out an aasimar character, consider the nature of that character's angelic guide. The Angelic Guide tables offer names and natures that you can use to flesh out your character's guide.</p>
			<h4>CONFLICTED SOULS</h4>
			<p>Despite its celestial origin, an aasimar is mortal and possesses free will. Most aasimar follow their ordained path, but some grow to see their abilities as a curse. These disaffected aasimar are typically content to turn away from the world, but a few become agents of evil. In their minds, their exposure to celestial powers amounted to little more than brainwashing.</p>
			<p class="indent">Evil aasimar make deadly foes. The radiant power they once commanded becomes corrupted into a horrid, draining magic. And their angelic guides abandon them.</p>
			<p class="indent">Even aasimar wholly dedicated to good sometimes feel torn between two worlds. The angels that guide them see the world from a distant perch. An aasimar who wishes to stop and help a town recover from a drought might be told by an angelic guide to push forward on a greater quest. To a distant angel, saving a few commoners might pale in comparison to defeating a cult of Orcus. An aasimar's guide is wise but not infallible.</p>
			<h4>AASIMAR TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Your aasimar character has the following racial traits.<br />
				<span class="feature">Age.</span>Aasimar mature at the same rate as humans, but they can live up to 160 years.<br />
				<span class="feature">Size.</span>Your size is Medium (about 4-7 feet tall) or Small (about 2-4 feet tall), chosen when you select this species.<br />
				<span class="feature">Speed.</span>Your base walking speed is 30 feet.<br />        
				<span class="feature">Darkvision.</span>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.<br />
				<span class="feature">Celestial Resistance.</span> You have resistance to Necrotic damage and Radiant damage.<br />
				<span class="feature">Healing Hands.</span> As a Magic action, you touch a creature and roll a number of d4s equal to your Proficiency Bonus. The creature regains a number of Hit Points equal to the total rolled. Once you use this trait, you can’t use it again until you finish a Long Rest.<br />
				<span class="feature">Light Bearer.</span> You know the Light cantrip. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for it.<br />      
				<span class="feature">Celestial Revelation.</span> When you reach character level 3, you can transform as a Bonus Action. The transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it (no action required). Once you transform, you can’t do so again until you finish a Long Rest. Additionally, once on each of your turns before the transformation ends, you can deal extra damage to a target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra damage equals your Proficiency Bonus, and the extra damage’s type is either Necrotic or Radiant determined by the transformation.<br />
			</p>        
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Aseir, Bardeid, Haseid, Khemed, Mehmen, Sudeiman, Zasheir</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Atala, Ceidil, Hama, Jasmal, Meilil, Seipora, Yasheira, Zasheida</set>
			<set name="names" type="surname">Basha, Dumein, Jassan, Khalid, Mostana, Pashar, Rein</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}} {{surname}}</set>   
			<set name="height" modifier="2d10">4'8"</set>
			<set name="weight" modifier="2d4">110 lb.</set>   
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Size" supports="Aasimar Size" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_DARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" />
			<select type="Language" name="Languages" supports="Standard Languages" number="2" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_CELESTIAL_RESISTANCE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_HEALING_HANDS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_LIGHT_BEARER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_CELESTIAL_REVELATION" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Medium" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_SIZE_MEDIUM">
		<supports>Aasimar Size</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your size is Medium (about 4-7 feet tall).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Small" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_SIZE_SMALL">
		<supports>Aasimar Size</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your size is Small (about 2-4 feet tall).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_SMALL" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Darkvision" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_DARKVISION">
		<description>
			<p>You have Darkvision with a range of 60 feet.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have Darkvision with a range of 60 feet.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Celestial Resistance" type="Racial Trait" source="Player's Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_CELESTIAL_RESISTANCE">
		<description>
			<p>You have resistance to Necrotic damage and Radiant damage.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have resistance to Necrotic damage and Radiant damage.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<!--<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_NECROTIC" />
			<grant type="Condition" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_RESISTANCE_RADIANT" />-->
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Healing Hands" type="Racial Trait" source="Player's Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_HEALING_HANDS">
		<description>
			<p>As a Magic action, you touch a creature and roll a number of d4s equal to your Proficiency Bonus. The creature regains a number of Hit Points equal to the total rolled. Once you use this trait, you can’t use it again until you finish a Long Rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Magic Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>You can touch a creature and cause it to regain {{proficiency}}d4 Hit Points.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Light Bearer" type="Racial Trait" source="Player's Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_LIGHT_BEARER">
		<description>
			<p>You know the Light cantrip. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for it.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You know the Light cantrip. (Spellcasting: Charisma)</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_LIGHT" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Celestial Revelation" type="Racial Trait" source="Player's Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_CELESTIAL_REVELATION">
		<requirements>[level:3]</requirements>
		<description>
			<p>When you reach character level 3, you can transform as a Bonus Action. The transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it (no action required). Once you transform, you can’t do so again until you finish a Long Rest. Additionally, once on each of your turns before the transformation ends, you can deal extra damage to a target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra damage equals your Proficiency Bonus, and the extra damage’s type is either Necrotic for Necrotic Shroud or Radiant for Heavenly Wings and Inner Radiance.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false"/>
		<rules>
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Celestial Revelation" supports="Aasimar Celestial Revelation" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Heavenly Wings" type="Racial Trait" source="Player's Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_HEAVENLY_WINGS">
		<supports>Aasimar Celestial Revelation</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You can transform as a Bonus Action. Two spectral wings sprout from your back and you have a Fly Speed equal to your Speed. The transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it (no action required). Once you transform, you can’t do so again until you finish a Long Rest. Additionally, once on each of your turns before the transformation ends, you can deal extra damage to a target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra damage equals your Proficiency Bonus, and the extra damage’s type is Radiant.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>Two spectral wings sprout from your back and you have a Fly Speed equal to your Speed. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it (no action required). Once on each of your turns, you can deal {{proficiency}} extra Radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Inner Radiance" type="Racial Trait" source="Player's Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_INNER_RADIANCE">
		<supports>Aasimar Celestial Revelation</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You can transform as a Bonus Action. Searing light radiates from your eyes and mouth and you shed Bright Light in a 10-foot radius and Dim Light for an additional 10 feet. The transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it (no action required). Once you transform, you can’t do so again until you finish a Long Rest. Additionally, once on each of your turns before the transformation ends, you can deal extra damage to a target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra damage equals your Proficiency Bonus, and the extra damage’s type is Radiant.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>Searing light radiates from your eyes and mouth and you shed Bright Light in a 10-foot radius and Dim Light for an additional 10 feet. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it (no action required). Once on each of your turns, you can deal {{proficiency}} extra Radiant damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Necrotic Shroud" type="Racial Trait" source="Player's Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_AASIMAR_NECROTIC_SHROUD">
		<supports>Aasimar Celestial Revelation</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You can transform as a Bonus Action. Your eyes briefly become pools of darkness, and flightless wings sprout from your back. Creatures other than your allies within 10 feet of you must succeed on a Charisma saving throw (DC 8 plus your Charisma modifier and Proficiency Bonus) or have the Frightened condition until the end of your next turn. The transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it (no action required). Once you transform, you can’t do so again until you finish a Long Rest. Additionally, once on each of your turns before the transformation ends, you can deal extra damage to a target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell. The extra damage equals your Proficiency Bonus, and the extra damage’s type is Necrotic.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
			<description>Your eyes briefly become pools of darkness, and flightless wings sprout from your back. Creatures other than your allies within 10 feet of you must each succeed on a Charisma saving throw (DC {{necrotic shroud:dc}}) or have the Frightened condition until the end of your next turn. Your transformation lasts for 1 minute or until you end it (no action required). Once on each of your turns, you can deal {{proficiency}} extra Necrotic damage to one target when you deal damage to it with an attack or a spell.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="8" />
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="proficiency" />
			<stat name="necrotic shroud:dc" value="charisma:modifier" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	
</elements>
