<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<element name="Gnome" type="Race" source="Player’s Handbook (2024)" id="ID_SPECIES_GNOME">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">A constant hum of busy activity pervades the warrens and neighborhoods where gnomes form their closeknit communities. Louder sounds punctuate the hum: a crunch of grinding gears here, a minor explosion there, a yelp of surprise or triumph, and especially bursts of laughter. Gnomes take delight in life, enjoying every moment of invention, exploration, investigation, creation, and play.</p>
			<h4>VIBRANT EXPRESSION</h4>
			<p>A gnome’s energy and enthusiasm for living shines through every inch of his or her tiny body. Gnomes average slightly over 3 feet tall and weigh 40 to 45 pounds. Their tan or brown faces are usually adorned with broad smiles (beneath their prodigious noses), and their bright eyes shine with excitement. Their fair hair has a tendency to stick out in every direction, as if expressing the gnome’s insatiable interest in everything around.</p>
			<p class="indent">A gnome’s personality is writ large in his or her appearance. A male gnome’s beard, in contrast to his wild hair, is kept carefully trimmed but often styled into curious forks or neat points. A gnome’s clothing, though usually made in modest earth tones, is elaborately decorated with embroidery, embossing, or gleaming jewels.</p>
			<h4>DELIGHTED DEDICATION</h4>
			<p>As far as gnomes are concerned, being alive is a wonderful thing, and they squeeze every ounce of enjoyment out of their three to five centuries of life. Humans might wonder about getting bored over the course of such a long life, and elves take plenty of time to savor the beauties of the world in their long years, but gnomes seem to worry that even with all that time, they can’t get in enough of the things they want to do and see.</p>
			<p class="indent">Gnomes speak as if they can’t get the thoughts out of their heads fast enough. Even as they offer ideas and opinions on a range of subjects, they still manage to listen carefully to others, adding the appropriate exclamations of surprise and appreciation along the way.</p>
			<p class="indent">Though gnomes love jokes of all kinds, particularly puns and pranks, they’re just as dedicated to the more serious tasks they undertake. Many gnomes are skilled engineers, alchemists, tinkers, and inventors. They’re willing to make mistakes and laugh at themselves in the process of perfecting what they do, taking bold (sometimes foolhardy) risks and dreaming large.</p>
			<h4>BRIGHT BURROWS</h4>
			<p>Gnomes make their homes in hilly, wooded lands. They live underground but get more fresh air than dwarves do, enjoying the natural, living world on the surface whenever they can. Their homes are well hidden by both clever construction and simple illusions. Welcome visitors are quickly ushered into the bright, warm burrows. Those who are not welcome are unlikely to find the burrows in the first place.</p>
			<p class="indent">Gnomes who settle in human lands are commonly gemcutters, engineers, sages, or tinkers. Some human families retain gnome tutors, ensuring that their pupils enjoy a mix of serious learning and delighted enjoyment. A gnome might tutor several generations of a single human family over the course of his or her long life.</p>
			<h4>GNOME NAMES</h4>
			<p>Gnomes love names, and most have half a dozen or so. A gnome's mother, father, clan elder, aunts, and uncles each give the gnome a name, and various nicknames from just about everyone else might or might not stick over time. Gnome names are typically variants on the names of ancestors or distant relatives, though some are purely new inventions. When dealing with humans and others who are “stuffy” about names, a gnome learns to use no more than three names: a personal name, a clan name, and a nickname, choosing the one in each category that’s the most fun to say.</p>
			<p><b>Male Names:</b> Alston, Alvyn, Boddynock, Brocc, Burgell, Dimble, Eldon, Erky, Fonkin, Frug, Gerbo, Gimble, Glim, Jebeddo, Kellen, Namfoodle, Orryn, Roondar, Seebo, Sindri, Warryn, Wrenn, Zook <br/>
			<b>Female Names:</b> Bimpnottin, Breena, Caramip, Carlin, Donella, Duvamil, Ella, Ellyjobell, Ellywick, Lilli, Loopmottin, Lorilla, Mardnab, Nissa, Nyx, Oda, Orla, Roywyn, Shamil, Tana, Waywocket, Zanna <br/>
			<b>Clan Names:</b> Beren, Daergel, Folkor, Garrick, Nackle, Murnig, Ningel, Raulnor, Scheppen, Timbers, Turen <br/>
			<b>Nicknames:</b> Aleslosh, Ashhearth, Badger, Cloak, Doublelock, Filchbatter, Fnipper, Ku, Nim, Oneshoe, Pock, Sparklegem, Stumbleduck</p>
			<h4>SEEING THE WORLD</h4>
			<p>Curious and impulsive, gnomes might take up adventuring as a way to see the world or for the love of exploring. As lovers of gems and other fine items, some gnomes take to adventuring as a quick, if dangerous, path to wealth. Regardless of what spurs them to adventure, gnomes who adopt this way of life eke as much enjoyment out of it as they do out of any other activity they undertake, sometimes to the great annoyance of their adventuring companions.</p>
			<h4>GNOME TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Your gnome character has certain characteristics in common with all other gnomes.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>Age.</i></b> Gnomes mature at the same rate humans do, and most are expected to settle down into an adult life by around age 40. They can live 350 to almost 500 years.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>Size.</i></b> Gnomes are usually about 3-4 feet tall. Your size is Small.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>Speed.</i></b> Your base walking speed is 30 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>Darkvision.</i></b> Accustomed to life underground, you have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>Gnome Cunning.</i></b> You have advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws against magic.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>Gnomish Lineage.</i></b> You are part of a lineage that grants you supernatural abilities, either Forest Gnome or Rock Gnome; whichever one you choose, Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for the spells you cast with this trait (choose the ability when you select the lineage).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<setters>
			<set name="names" type="male">Alston, Alvyn, Boddynock, Brocc, Burgell, Dimble, Eldon, Erky, Fonkin, Frug, Gerbo, Gimble, Glim, Jebeddo, Kellen, Namfoodle, Orryn, Roondar, Seebo, Sindri, Warryn, Wrenn, Zook</set>
			<set name="names" type="female">Bimpnottin, Breena, Caramip, Carlin, Donella, Duvamil, Ella, Ellyjobell, Ellywick, Lilli, Loopmottin, Lorilla, Mardnab, Nissa, Nyx, Oda, Orla, Roywyn, Shamil, Tana, Waywocket, Zanna</set>
			<set name="names" type="clan">Beren, Daergel, Folkor, Garrick, Nackle, Murnig, Ningel, Raulnor, Scheppen, Timbers, Turen</set>
			<set name="names" type="nickname">Aleslosh, Ashhearth, Badger, Cloak, Doublelock, Filchbatter, Fnipper, Ku, Nim, Oneshoe, Pock, Sparklegem, Stumbleduck</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{name}} '{{nickname}}' {{clan}}</set>
			<set name="height" modifier="2d4">2'11"</set>
			<set name="weight" modifier="1">35 lb.</set>
		</setters>
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_SMALL" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" />
			<select type="Language" name="Languages" supports="Standard Languages" number="2" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_GNOME_CUNNING" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_GNOMISH_LINEAGE" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Gnome Cunning" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook (2024)" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_GNOME_CUNNING">
		<description>
			<p>You have advantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have advantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Gnomish Lineage" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook (2024)" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_GNOMISH_LINEAGE">
		<description>
			<p>You are part of a lineage that grants you supernatural abilities, either Forest Gnome or Rock Gnome; whichever one you choose, Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for the spells you cast with this trait (choose the ability when you select the lineage).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Gnomish Lineage" supports="Gnomish Lineage" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Forest Gnome" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook (2024)" id="ID_GNOMISH_LINEAGE_FOREST_GNOME">
		<supports>Gnomish Lineage</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You know the Minor Illusion cantrip. You also always have the Speak with Animals spell prepared. You can cast it without a spell slot a number of times equal to your Proficiency Bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest. You can also use any spell slots you have to cast the spell.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You know the Minor Illusion cantrip and the Speak with Animals spell which you always have prepared. You can cast it without a spell slot {{proficiency}} times per Long Rest. You can also use any spell slots you have to cast the spell.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Spellcasting Ability (Gnomish Lineage)" supports="Gnomish Lineage Ability" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MINOR_ILLUSION" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_SPEAK_WITH_ANIMALS" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Rock Gnome" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook (2024)" id="ID_GNOMISH_LINEAGE_ROCK_GNOME">
		<supports>Gnomish Lineage</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You know the Mending and Prestidigitation cantrips. In addition, you can spend 10 minutes casting Prestidigitation to create a Tiny clockwork device (AC 5, 1 HP), such as a toy, fire starter, or music box. When you create the device, you determine its function by choosing one effect from Prestidigitation; the device produces that effect whenever you or another creature takes a Bonus Action to activate it with a touch. If the chosen effect has options within it, you choose one of those options for the device when you create it. For example, if you choose the spell’s ignite-extinguish effect, you determine whether the device ignites or extinguishes fire; the device doesn’t do both. You can have three such devices in existence at a time, and each falls apart 8 hours after its creation or when you dismantle it with a touch as a Utilize action.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You know the Mending and Prestidigitation cantrips. You can spend 10 minutes casting Prestidigitation to create a Tiny clockwork device (AC 5, 1 HP), such as a toy, fire starter, or music box. When you create the device, you determine its function by choosing one effect from Prestidigitation; the device produces that effect whenever you or another creature takes a Bonus Action to activate it. If the chosen effect has options, you choose one of those for the device when you create it. You can have three such devices at a time, and each falls apart after 8 hours or when you dismantle it with a Utilize action.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Spellcasting Ability (Gnomish Lineage)" supports="Gnomish Lineage Ability" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_MENDING" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_PRESTIDIGITATION" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Intelligence" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_GNOMISH_LINEAGE_INTELLIGENCE">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<supports>Gnomish Lineage Ability</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Intelligence.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Wisdom" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_GNOMISH_LINEAGE_WISDOM">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<supports>Gnomish Lineage Ability</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Wisdom.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Charisma" type="Racial Trait" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_SPECIES_TRAIT_GNOMISH_LINEAGE_CHARISMA">
		<compendium display="false" />
		<supports>Gnomish Lineage Ability</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Your spellcasting ability for these spells is Charisma.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	
</elements>
